<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml language="en"><file id="1">
  <head>
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/knut_haanaes_two_reasons_companies_fail_and_how_to_avoid_them</url>
    <pagesize>72832</pagesize>
    <dtime>Fri Apr 01 00:57:03 CEST 2016</dtime>
    <encoding>UTF-8</encoding>
    <content-type>text/html; charset=utf-8</content-type>
    <keywords>talks, business, creativity, curiosity, goal-setting, innovation, motivation, potential, success, work</keywords>
    <speaker>Knut Haanaes</speaker>
    <talkid>2470</talkid>
    <videourl>http://download.ted.com/talks/KnutHaanaes_2015S.mp4</videourl>
    <videopath>talks/KnutHaanaes_2015S.mp4</videopath>
    <date>2015/06/30</date>
    <title>Knut Haanaes: Two reasons companies fail -- and how to avoid them</title>
    <description>TED Talk Subtitles and Transcript: Is it possible to run a company and reinvent it at the same time? For business strategist Knut Haanaes, the ability to innovate after becoming successful is the mark of a great organization. He shares insights on how to strike a balance between perfecting what we already know and exploring totally new ideas -- and lays out how to avoid two major strategy traps.</description>
    <transcription>
      <seekvideo id="1596">Here are two reasons companies fail:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="5208">they only do more of the same,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="8478">or they only do what's new.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="11613">To me the real, real solution to quality growth</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="16537">is figuring out the balance between two activities:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="20126">exploration and exploitation.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="23114">Both are necessary,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="24728">but it can be too much of a good thing.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="29154">Consider Facit.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="31061">I'm actually old enough to remember them.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="33489">Facit was a fantastic company.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="35999">They were born deep in the Swedish forest,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="38496">and they made the best mechanical calculators in the world.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="42524">Everybody used them.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="44798">And what did Facit do when the electronic calculator came along?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="49691">They continued doing exactly the same.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="52953">In six months, they went from maximum revenue ...</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="56695">and they were gone.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="58649">Gone.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="59824">To me, the irony about the Facit story</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="63720">is hearing about the Facit engineers,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="67010">who had bought cheap, small electronic calculators in Japan</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="72117">that they used to double-check their calculators.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="75802">(Laughter)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="77239">Facit did too much exploitation.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="80422">But exploration can go wild, too.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="82900">A few years back,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="84075">I worked closely alongside a European biotech company.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="88447">Let's call them OncoSearch.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="90830">The company was brilliant.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="92511">They had applications that promised to diagnose, even cure,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="97153">certain forms of blood cancer.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="100190">Every day was about creating something new.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="103744">They were extremely innovative,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="106272">and the mantra was, "When we only get it right,"</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="109172">or even, "We want it perfect."</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="112687">The sad thing is,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="114568">before they became perfect --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="116490">even good enough --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="118443">they became obsolete.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="121331">OncoSearch did too much exploration.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="125602">I first heard about exploration and exploitation about 15 years ago,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="131381">when I worked as a visiting scholar at Stanford University.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="135428">The founder of the idea is Jim March.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="138168">And to me the power of the idea is its practicality.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="143168">Exploration.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="144847">Exploration is about coming up with what's new.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="148772">It's about search,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="150027">it's about discovery,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="151494">it's about new products,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="153080">it's about new innovations.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="155591">It's about changing our frontiers.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="159408">Our heroes are people who have done exploration:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="162867">Madame Curie,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="164232">Picasso,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="165414">Neil Armstrong,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="166612">Sir Edmund Hillary, etc.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="169210">I come from Norway;</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="171569">all our heroes are explorers, and they deserve to be.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="177364">We all know that exploration is risky.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="180454">We don't know the answers,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="182297">we don't know if we're going to find them,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="184392">and we know that the risks are high.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="186693">Exploitation is the opposite.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="188608">Exploitation is taking the knowledge we have</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="191709">and making good, better.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="194344">Exploitation is about making our trains run on time.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="197984">It's about making good products faster and cheaper.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="202900">Exploitation is not risky --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="205911">in the short term.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="207595">But if we only exploit,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="209425">it's very risky in the long term.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="212503">And I think we all have memories of the famous pop groups</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="216285">who keep singing the same songs again and again,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="219719">until they become obsolete or even pathetic.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="224204">That's the risk of exploitation.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="228667">So if we take a long-term perspective, we explore.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="233427">If we take a short-term perspective, we exploit.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="237693">Small children, they explore all day.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="240880">All day it's about exploration.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="243326">As we grow older,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="244763">we explore less because we have more knowledge to exploit on.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="249820">The same goes for companies.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="252706">Companies become, by nature, less innovative</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="256594">as they become more competent.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="259239">And this is, of course, a big worry to CEOs.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="263410">And I hear very often questions phrased in different ways.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="267943">For example,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="269125">"How can I both effectively run and reinvent my company?"</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="274557">Or, "How can I make sure</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="276475">that our company changes before we become obsolete</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="280860">or are hit by a crisis?"</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="283584">So, doing one well is difficult.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="286164">Doing both well as the same time is art --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="289955">pushing both exploration and exploitation.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="293138">So one thing we've found</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="294658">is only about two percent of companies are able to effectively explore</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="301378">and exploit at the same time, in parallel.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="305570">But when they do,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="307478">the payoffs are huge.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="310337">So we have lots of great examples.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="312750">We have Nestlé creating Nespresso,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="315490">we have Lego going into animated films,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="318536">Toyota creating the hybrids,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="320966">Unilever pushing into sustainability --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="323461">there are lots of examples, and the benefits are huge.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="327812">Why is balancing so difficult?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="330846">I think it's difficult because there are so many traps</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="333500">that keep us where we are.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="335975">So I'll talk about two, but there are many.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="339098">So let's talk about the perpetual search trap.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="342616">We discover something,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="344452">but we don't have the patience or the persistence</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="347331">to get at it and make it work.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="349683">So instead of staying with it, we create something new.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="352852">But the same goes for that,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="354176">then we're in the vicious circle</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="355951">of actually coming up with ideas but being frustrated.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="360381">OncoSearch was a good example.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="362725">A famous example is, of course, Xerox.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="366607">But we don't only see this in companies.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="368731">We see this in the public sector as well.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="371726">We all know that any kind of effective reform of education,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="377472">research, health care, even defense,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="379923">takes 10, 15, maybe 20 years to work.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="383766">But still, we change much more often.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="387090">We really don't give them the chance.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="390424">Another trap is the success trap.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="394808">Facit fell into the success trap.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="398275">They literally held the future in their hands,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="401549">but they couldn't see it.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="402787">They were simply so good at making what they loved doing,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="406566">that they wouldn't change.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="409187">We are like that, too.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="410504">When we know something well, it's difficult to change.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="414872">Bill Gates has said:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="417016">"Success is a lousy teacher.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="420040">It seduces us into thinking we cannot fail."</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="424457">That's the challenge with success.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="427886">So I think there are some lessons, and I think they apply to us.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="431364">And they apply to our companies.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="433570">The first lesson is: get ahead of the crisis.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="437949">And any company that's able to innovate</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="440542">is actually able to also buy an insurance in the future.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="444709">Netflix -- they could so easily have been content</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="447596">with earlier generations of distribution,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="450484">but they always -- and I think they will always --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="453065">keep pushing for the next battle.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="455572">I see other companies that say,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="457961">"I'll win the next innovation cycle, whatever it takes."</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="463635">Second one: think in multiple time scales.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="466918">I'll share a chart with you,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="468280">and I think it's a wonderful one.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="470461">Any company we look at,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="472198">taking a one-year perspective</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="474021">and looking at the valuation of the company,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="476322">innovation typically accounts for only about 30 percent.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="480187">So when we think one year,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="481598">innovation isn't really that important.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="484490">Move ahead, take a 10-year perspective on the same company --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="488082">suddenly, innovation and ability to renew account for 70 percent.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="494253">But companies can't choose.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="495754">They need to fund the journey and lead the long term.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="500746">Third:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="502304">invite talent.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="503974">I don't think it's possible for any of us</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="506546">to be able to balance exploration and exploitation by ourselves.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="511100">I think it's a team sport.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="512830">I think we need to allow challenging.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="516273">I think the mark of a great company is being open to be challenged,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="521187">and the mark of a good corporate board is to constructively challenge.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="526264">I think that's also what good parenting is about.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="530858">Last one: be skeptical of success.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="534133">Maybe it's useful to think back at the old triumph marches in Rome,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="540490">when the generals, after a big victory,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="544010">were given their celebration.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="546754">Riding into Rome on the carriage,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="549513">they always had a companion whispering in their ear,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="553759">"Remember, you're only human."</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="557923">So I hope I made the point:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="560701">balancing exploration and exploitation</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="563747">has a huge payoff.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="565218">But it's difficult, and we need to be conscious.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="568338">I want to just point out two questions that I think are useful.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="573397">First question is, looking at your own company:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="577446">In which areas do you see that the company is at the risk</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="581780">of falling into success traps,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="584048">of just going on autopilot?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="587105">And what can you do to challenge?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="591639">Second question is:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="594530">When did I explore something new last,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="597815">and what kind of effect did it have on me?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="600814">Is that something I should do more of?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="603596">In my case, yes.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="606657">So let me leave you with this.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="608692">Whether you're an explorer by nature</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="611997">or whether you tend to exploit what you already know,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="615923">don't forget: the beauty is in the balance.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="621392">Thank you.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="622576">(Applause)</seekvideo>
    </transcription>
    <wordnum>1336</wordnum>
    <charnum>7589</charnum>
  </head>
  <content>Here are two reasons companies fail: they only do more of the same, or they only do what's new.
To me the real, real solution to quality growth is figuring out the balance between two activities: exploration and exploitation. Both are necessary, but it can be too much of a good thing.
Consider Facit. I'm actually old enough to remember them. Facit was a fantastic company. They were born deep in the Swedish forest, and they made the best mechanical calculators in the world. Everybody used them. And what did Facit do when the electronic calculator came along? They continued doing exactly the same. In six months, they went from maximum revenue ... and they were gone. Gone.
To me, the irony about the Facit story is hearing about the Facit engineers, who had bought cheap, small electronic calculators in Japan that they used to double-check their calculators.
(Laughter)
Facit did too much exploitation. But exploration can go wild, too.
A few years back, I worked closely alongside a European biotech company. Let's call them OncoSearch. The company was brilliant. They had applications that promised to diagnose, even cure, certain forms of blood cancer. Every day was about creating something new. They were extremely innovative, and the mantra was, "When we only get it right," or even, "We want it perfect." The sad thing is, before they became perfect -- even good enough -- they became obsolete. OncoSearch did too much exploration.
I first heard about exploration and exploitation about 15 years ago, when I worked as a visiting scholar at Stanford University. The founder of the idea is Jim March. And to me the power of the idea is its practicality.
Exploration. Exploration is about coming up with what's new. It's about search, it's about discovery, it's about new products, it's about new innovations. It's about changing our frontiers. Our heroes are people who have done exploration: Madame Curie, Picasso, Neil Armstrong, Sir Edmund Hillary, etc. I come from Norway; all our heroes are explorers, and they deserve to be. We all know that exploration is risky. We don't know the answers, we don't know if we're going to find them, and we know that the risks are high.
Exploitation is the opposite. Exploitation is taking the knowledge we have and making good, better. Exploitation is about making our trains run on time. It's about making good products faster and cheaper. Exploitation is not risky -- in the short term. But if we only exploit, it's very risky in the long term. And I think we all have memories of the famous pop groups who keep singing the same songs again and again, until they become obsolete or even pathetic. That's the risk of exploitation.
So if we take a long-term perspective, we explore. If we take a short-term perspective, we exploit. Small children, they explore all day. All day it's about exploration. As we grow older, we explore less because we have more knowledge to exploit on. The same goes for companies. Companies become, by nature, less innovative as they become more competent.
And this is, of course, a big worry to CEOs. And I hear very often questions phrased in different ways. For example, "How can I both effectively run and reinvent my company?" Or, "How can I make sure that our company changes before we become obsolete or are hit by a crisis?" So, doing one well is difficult. Doing both well as the same time is art -- pushing both exploration and exploitation.
So one thing we've found is only about two percent of companies are able to effectively explore and exploit at the same time, in parallel. But when they do, the payoffs are huge. So we have lots of great examples. We have Nestlé creating Nespresso, we have Lego going into animated films, Toyota creating the hybrids, Unilever pushing into sustainability -- there are lots of examples, and the benefits are huge.
Why is balancing so difficult? I think it's difficult because there are so many traps that keep us where we are. So I'll talk about two, but there are many.
So let's talk about the perpetual search trap. We discover something, but we don't have the patience or the persistence to get at it and make it work. So instead of staying with it, we create something new. But the same goes for that, then we're in the vicious circle of actually coming up with ideas but being frustrated. OncoSearch was a good example. A famous example is, of course, Xerox. But we don't only see this in companies. We see this in the public sector as well. We all know that any kind of effective reform of education, research, health care, even defense, takes 10, 15, maybe 20 years to work. But still, we change much more often. We really don't give them the chance.
Another trap is the success trap. Facit fell into the success trap. They literally held the future in their hands, but they couldn't see it. They were simply so good at making what they loved doing, that they wouldn't change. We are like that, too. When we know something well, it's difficult to change. Bill Gates has said: "Success is a lousy teacher. It seduces us into thinking we cannot fail." That's the challenge with success.
So I think there are some lessons, and I think they apply to us. And they apply to our companies. The first lesson is: get ahead of the crisis. And any company that's able to innovate is actually able to also buy an insurance in the future. Netflix -- they could so easily have been content with earlier generations of distribution, but they always -- and I think they will always -- keep pushing for the next battle. I see other companies that say, "I'll win the next innovation cycle, whatever it takes."
Second one: think in multiple time scales. I'll share a chart with you, and I think it's a wonderful one. Any company we look at, taking a one-year perspective and looking at the valuation of the company, innovation typically accounts for only about 30 percent. So when we think one year, innovation isn't really that important. Move ahead, take a 10-year perspective on the same company -- suddenly, innovation and ability to renew account for 70 percent. But companies can't choose. They need to fund the journey and lead the long term.
Third: invite talent. I don't think it's possible for any of us to be able to balance exploration and exploitation by ourselves. I think it's a team sport. I think we need to allow challenging. I think the mark of a great company is being open to be challenged, and the mark of a good corporate board is to constructively challenge. I think that's also what good parenting is about.
Last one: be skeptical of success. Maybe it's useful to think back at the old triumph marches in Rome, when the generals, after a big victory, were given their celebration. Riding into Rome on the carriage, they always had a companion whispering in their ear, "Remember, you're only human."
So I hope I made the point: balancing exploration and exploitation has a huge payoff. But it's difficult, and we need to be conscious.
I want to just point out two questions that I think are useful. First question is, looking at your own company: In which areas do you see that the company is at the risk of falling into success traps, of just going on autopilot? And what can you do to challenge?
Second question is: When did I explore something new last, and what kind of effect did it have on me? Is that something I should do more of? In my case, yes.
So let me leave you with this. Whether you're an explorer by nature or whether you tend to exploit what you already know, don't forget: the beauty is in the balance.
Thank you.
(Applause)</content>
</file>
<file id="2">
  <head>
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lisa_nip_how_humans_could_evolve_to_survive_in_space</url>
    <pagesize>73252</pagesize>
    <dtime>Fri Apr 01 00:57:12 CEST 2016</dtime>
    <encoding>UTF-8</encoding>
    <content-type>text/html; charset=utf-8</content-type>
    <keywords>talks, Planets, TEDx, bacteria, biology, engineering, environment, evolution, exploration, future, innovation, intelligence, microbiology, nature, potential, science</keywords>
    <speaker>Lisa Nip</speaker>
    <talkid>2471</talkid>
    <videourl>http://download.ted.com/talks/LisaNip_2015X.mp4</videourl>
    <videopath>talks/LisaNip_2015X.mp4</videopath>
    <date>2015/11/14</date>
    <title>Lisa Nip: How humans could evolve to survive in space</title>
    <description>TED Talk Subtitles and Transcript: If we hope to one day leave Earth and explore the universe, our bodies are going to have to get a lot better at surviving the harsh conditions of space. Using synthetic biology, Lisa Nip hopes to harness special powers from microbes on Earth -- such as the ability to withstand radiation -- to make humans more fit for exploring space. "We're approaching a time during which we'll have the capacity to decide our own genetic destiny," Nip says. "Augmenting the human body with new abilities is no longer a question of how, but of when."</description>
    <transcription>
      <seekvideo id="1800">So there are lands few and far between on Earth itself</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="5360">that are hospitable to humans by any measure,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="9440">but survive we have.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="11800">Our primitive ancestors, when they found their homes and livelihood endangered,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="16079">they dared to make their way into unfamiliar territories</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="19240">in search of better opportunities.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="21760">And as the descendants of these explorers,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="24000">we have their nomadic blood coursing through our own veins.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="28040">But at the same time,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="29520">distracted by our bread and circuses</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="31640">and embroiled in the wars that we have waged on each other,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="35840">it seems that we have forgotten this desire to explore.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="40320">We, as a species, we're evolved uniquely</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="44960">for Earth, on Earth, and by Earth,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="49680">and so content are we with our living conditions</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="52840">that we have grown complacent and just too busy</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="56280">to notice that its resources are finite,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="58760">and that our Sun's life is also finite.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="62400">While Mars and all the movies made in its name</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="65200">have reinvigorated the ethos for space travel,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="68240">few of us seem to truly realize that our species' fragile constitution</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="73640">is woefully unprepared for long duration journeys into space.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="78160">Let us take a trek to your local national forest</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="80440">for a quick reality check.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="82280">So just a quick show of hands here:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="84000">how many of you think you would be able to survive in this lush wilderness</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="87600">for a few days?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="90000">Well, that's a lot of you.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="91320">How about a few weeks?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="94000">That's a decent amount.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="95280">How about a few months?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="97600">That's pretty good too.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="99120">Now, let us imagine that this local national forest</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="101800">experiences an eternal winter.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="105360">Same questions: how many of you think you would be able to survive for a few days?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="110280">That's quite a lot.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="111720">How about a few weeks?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="114400">So for a fun twist, let us imagine that the only source of water available</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="119120">is trapped as frozen blocks miles below the surface.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="123080">Soil nutrients are so minimal that no vegetation can be found,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="127200">and of course hardly any atmosphere exists to speak of.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="133240">Such examples are only a few of the many challenges we would face</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="137400">on a planet like Mars.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="140000">So how do we steel ourselves for voyages whose destinations are so far removed</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="145200">from a tropical vacation?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="147520">Will we continuously ship supplies from Planet Earth?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="150880">Build space elevators, or impossible miles of transport belts</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="154360">that tether your planet of choice to our home planet?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="158160">And how do we grow things like food that grew up on Earth like us?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="165080">But I'm getting ahead of myself.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="167560">In our species' journey to find a new home under a new sun,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="171720">we are more likely than not going to be spending much time</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="175600">in the journey itself,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="177840">in space,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="179480">on a ship, a hermetic flying can,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="183120">possibly for many generations.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="185480">The longest continuous amount of time that any human has spent in space</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="188920">is in the vicinity of 12 to 14 months.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="192600">From astronauts' experiences in space,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="194960">we know that spending time in a microgravity environment</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="198760">means bone loss, muscle atrophy, cardiovascular problems,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="203360">among many other complications</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="204960">that range for the physiological to the psychological.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="209200">And what about macrogravity,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="210640">or any other variation in gravitational pull</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="213160">of the planet that we find ourselves on?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="216560">In short, our cosmic voyages will be fraught with dangers</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="220120">both known and unknown.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="222960">So far we've been looking to this new piece of mechanical technology</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="227000">or that great next generation robot</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="229280">as part of a lineup to ensure our species safe passage in space.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="233600">Wonderful as they are, I believe the time has come</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="236560">for us to complement these bulky electronic giants</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="240840">with what nature has already invented:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="244320">the microbe,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="245720">a single-celled organism that is itself a self-generating, self-replenishing,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="250960">living machine.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="252760">It requires fairly little to maintain,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="255200">offers much flexibility in design</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="257120">and only asks to be carried in a single plastic tube.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="261399">The field of study that has enabled us to utilize the capabilities of the microbe</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="265280">is known as synthetic biology.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="267520">It comes from molecular biology, which has given us antibiotics, vaccines</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="271560">and better ways to observe the physiological nuances</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="274880">of the human body.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="276520">Using the tools of synthetic biology,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="278520">we can now edit the genes of nearly any organism,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="281480">microscopic or not,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="283440">with incredible speed and fidelity.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="286760">Given the limitations of our man-made machines,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="289680">synthetic biology will be a means for us to engineer not only our food,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="293680">our fuel and our environment,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="296440">but also ourselves</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="298760">to compensate for our physical inadequacies</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="301400">and to ensure our survival in space.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="305000">To give you an example</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="306240">of how we can use synthetic biology for space exploration,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="309080">let us return to the Mars environment.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="312160">The Martian soil composition is similar to that of Hawaiian volcanic ash,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="316920">with trace amounts of organic material.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="319400">Let's say, hypothetically,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="321680">what if martian soil could actually support plant growth</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="324440">without using Earth-derived nutrients?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="327360">The first question we should probably ask is,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="329480">how would we make our plants cold-tolerant?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="331880">Because, on average, the temperature on Mars</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="334000">is a very uninviting negative 60 degrees centigrade.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="338000">The next question we should ask is,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="339800">how do we make our plants drought-tolerant?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="342280">Considering that most of the water that forms as frost</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="345120">evaporates more quickly than I can say the word "evaporate."</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="349120">Well, it turns out we've already done things like this.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="352480">By borrowing genes for anti-freeze protein from fish</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="355800">and genes for drought tolerance from other plants like rice</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="359000">and then stitching them into the plants that need them,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="361720">we now have plants that can tolerate most droughts and freezes.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="365480">They're known on Earth as GMOs,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="368120">or genetically modified organisms,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="370680">and we rely on them to feed all the mouths of human civilization.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="376160">Nature does stuff like this already,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="379600">without our help.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="381160">We have simply found more precise ways to do it.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="385480">So why would we want to change the genetic makeup of plants for space?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="390120">Well, to not do so would mean needing to engineer</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="393720">endless acres of land on an entirely new planet</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="397160">by releasing trillions of gallons of atmospheric gasses</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="400680">and then constructing a giant glass dome to contain it all.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="404480">It's an unrealistic engineering enterprise</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="406560">that quickly becomes a high-cost cargo transport mission.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="411240">One of the best ways to ensure</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="412720">that we will have the food supplies and the air that we need</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="415840">is to bring with us organisms that have been engineered</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="418960">to adapt to new and harsh environments.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="422760">In essence, using engineered organisms to help us terraform a planet</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="426760">both in the short and long term.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="430400">These organisms can then also be engineered to make medicine or fuel.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="435920">So we can use synthetic biology to bring highly engineered plants with us,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="439680">but what else can we do?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="441880">Well, I mentioned earlier that we, as a species,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="444760">were evolved uniquely for planet Earth.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="447800">That fact has not changed much in the last five minutes</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="450440">that you were sitting here and I was standing there.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="453480">And so, if we were to dump any of us on Mars right this minute,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="457200">even given ample food, water, air</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="460720">and a suit,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="461960">we are likely to experience very unpleasant health problems</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="465360">from the amount of ionizing radiation that bombards the surface</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="468680">of planets like Mars that have little or nonexistent atmosphere.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="473280">Unless we plan to stay holed up underground</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="475320">for the duration of our stay on every new planet,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="478480">we must find better ways of protecting ourselves</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="481080">without needing to resort to wearing a suit of armor</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="483760">that weighs something equal to your own body weight,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="486240">or needing to hide behind a wall of lead.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="490240">So let us appeal to nature for inspiration.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="494200">Among the plethora of life here on Earth,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="496320">there's a subset of organisms known as extremophiles,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="499200">or lovers of extreme living conditions,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="501200">if you'll remember from high school biology.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="503680">And among these organisms is a bacterium by the name of Deinococcus radiodurans.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="509040">It is known to be able to withstand cold, dehydration, vacuum, acid,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="514440">and, most notably, radiation.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="517440">While its radiation tolerance mechanisms are known,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="520159">we have yet to adapt the relevant genes to mammals.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="523520">To do so is not particularly easy.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="526160">There are many facets that go into its radiation tolerance,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="529000">and it's not as simple as transferring one gene.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="531960">But given a little bit of human ingenuity</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="535240">and a little bit of time,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="536520">I think to do so is not very hard either.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="540000">Even if we borrow just a fraction of its ability to tolerate radiation,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="546400">it would be infinitely better than what we already have,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="549440">which is just the melanin in our skin.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="552560">Using the tools of synthetic biology,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="554600">we can harness Deinococcus radiodurans' ability</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="557640">to thrive under otherwise very lethal doses of radiation.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="563760">As difficult as it is to see,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="565920">homo sapiens, that is humans,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="569200">evolves every day,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="571520">and still continues to evolve.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="574360">Thousands of years of human evolution</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="576160">has not only given us humans like Tibetans,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="579160">who can thrive in low-oxygen conditions,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="581760">but also Argentinians, who can ingest and metabolize arsenic,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="586720">the chemical element that can kill the average human being.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="590360">Every day, the human body evolves by accidental mutations</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="594080">that equally accidentally allow certain humans</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="596960">to persevere in dismal situations.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="600160">But, and this is a big but,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="603480">such evolution requires two things that we may not always have,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="607680">or be able to afford,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="610120">and they are death and time.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="613560">In our species' struggle to find our place in the universe,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="616600">we may not always have the time necessary</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="619080">for the natural evolution of extra functions</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="621640">for survival on non-Earth planets.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="624360">We're living in what E.O. Wilson has termed the age of gene circumvention,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="628880">during which we remedy our genetic defects like cystic fibrosis or muscular dystrophy</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="634280">with temporary external supplements.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="637960">But with every passing day,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="639520">we approach the age of volitional evolution,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="642720">a time during which we as a species</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="644720">will have the capacity to decide for ourselves our own genetic destiny.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="650720">Augmenting the human body with new abilities</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="653080">is no longer a question of how,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="655920">but of when.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="658240">Using synthetic biology</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="659520">to change the genetic makeup of any living organisms,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="662640">especially our own,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="663880">is not without its moral and ethical quandaries.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="667280">Will engineering ourselves make us less human?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="670960">But then again, what is humanity</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="673240">but star stuff that happens to be conscious?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="677200">Where should human genius direct itself?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="680640">Surely it is a bit of a waste to sit back and marvel at it.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="685800">How do we use our knowledge</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="687160">to protect ourselves from the external dangers</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="690440">and then protect ourselves from ourselves?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="694400">I pose these questions</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="695840">not to engender the fear of science</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="698040">but to bring to light the many possibilities</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="700440">that science has afforded and continues to afford us.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="704760">We must coalesce as humans to discuss and embrace the solutions</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="708760">not only with caution</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="710640">but also with courage.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="714200">Mars is a destination,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="718440">but it will not be our last.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="721000">Our true final frontier is the line we must cross</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="723880">in deciding what we can and should make of our species' improbable intelligence.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="729880">Space is cold, brutal and unforgiving.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="735120">Our path to the stars will be rife with trials</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="737560">that will bring us to question not only who we are</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="740560">but where we will be going.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="743160">The answers will lie in our choice to use or abandon the technology</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="746760">that we have gleaned from life itself,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="748880">and it will define us for the remainder of our term in this universe.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="752760">Thank you.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="754000">(Applause)</seekvideo>
    </transcription>
    <wordnum>1889</wordnum>
    <charnum>10831</charnum>
  </head>
  <content>So there are lands few and far between on Earth itself that are hospitable to humans by any measure, but survive we have. Our primitive ancestors, when they found their homes and livelihood endangered, they dared to make their way into unfamiliar territories in search of better opportunities. And as the descendants of these explorers, we have their nomadic blood coursing through our own veins. But at the same time, distracted by our bread and circuses and embroiled in the wars that we have waged on each other, it seems that we have forgotten this desire to explore. We, as a species, we're evolved uniquely for Earth, on Earth, and by Earth, and so content are we with our living conditions that we have grown complacent and just too busy to notice that its resources are finite, and that our Sun's life is also finite. While Mars and all the movies made in its name have reinvigorated the ethos for space travel, few of us seem to truly realize that our species' fragile constitution is woefully unprepared for long duration journeys into space.
Let us take a trek to your local national forest for a quick reality check. So just a quick show of hands here: how many of you think you would be able to survive in this lush wilderness for a few days? Well, that's a lot of you. How about a few weeks? That's a decent amount. How about a few months? That's pretty good too. Now, let us imagine that this local national forest experiences an eternal winter. Same questions: how many of you think you would be able to survive for a few days? That's quite a lot. How about a few weeks? So for a fun twist, let us imagine that the only source of water available is trapped as frozen blocks miles below the surface. Soil nutrients are so minimal that no vegetation can be found, and of course hardly any atmosphere exists to speak of.
Such examples are only a few of the many challenges we would face on a planet like Mars. So how do we steel ourselves for voyages whose destinations are so far removed from a tropical vacation? Will we continuously ship supplies from Planet Earth? Build space elevators, or impossible miles of transport belts that tether your planet of choice to our home planet? And how do we grow things like food that grew up on Earth like us?
But I'm getting ahead of myself. In our species' journey to find a new home under a new sun, we are more likely than not going to be spending much time in the journey itself, in space, on a ship, a hermetic flying can, possibly for many generations.
The longest continuous amount of time that any human has spent in space is in the vicinity of 12 to 14 months. From astronauts' experiences in space, we know that spending time in a microgravity environment means bone loss, muscle atrophy, cardiovascular problems, among many other complications that range for the physiological to the psychological. And what about macrogravity, or any other variation in gravitational pull of the planet that we find ourselves on?
In short, our cosmic voyages will be fraught with dangers both known and unknown. So far we've been looking to this new piece of mechanical technology or that great next generation robot as part of a lineup to ensure our species safe passage in space. Wonderful as they are, I believe the time has come for us to complement these bulky electronic giants with what nature has already invented: the microbe, a single-celled organism that is itself a self-generating, self-replenishing, living machine. It requires fairly little to maintain, offers much flexibility in design and only asks to be carried in a single plastic tube.
The field of study that has enabled us to utilize the capabilities of the microbe is known as synthetic biology. It comes from molecular biology, which has given us antibiotics, vaccines and better ways to observe the physiological nuances of the human body. Using the tools of synthetic biology, we can now edit the genes of nearly any organism, microscopic or not, with incredible speed and fidelity. Given the limitations of our man-made machines, synthetic biology will be a means for us to engineer not only our food, our fuel and our environment, but also ourselves to compensate for our physical inadequacies and to ensure our survival in space.
To give you an example of how we can use synthetic biology for space exploration, let us return to the Mars environment. The Martian soil composition is similar to that of Hawaiian volcanic ash, with trace amounts of organic material. Let's say, hypothetically, what if martian soil could actually support plant growth without using Earth-derived nutrients? The first question we should probably ask is, how would we make our plants cold-tolerant? Because, on average, the temperature on Mars is a very uninviting negative 60 degrees centigrade. The next question we should ask is, how do we make our plants drought-tolerant? Considering that most of the water that forms as frost evaporates more quickly than I can say the word "evaporate." Well, it turns out we've already done things like this. By borrowing genes for anti-freeze protein from fish and genes for drought tolerance from other plants like rice and then stitching them into the plants that need them, we now have plants that can tolerate most droughts and freezes. They're known on Earth as GMOs, or genetically modified organisms, and we rely on them to feed all the mouths of human civilization. Nature does stuff like this already, without our help. We have simply found more precise ways to do it.
So why would we want to change the genetic makeup of plants for space? Well, to not do so would mean needing to engineer endless acres of land on an entirely new planet by releasing trillions of gallons of atmospheric gasses and then constructing a giant glass dome to contain it all. It's an unrealistic engineering enterprise that quickly becomes a high-cost cargo transport mission. One of the best ways to ensure that we will have the food supplies and the air that we need is to bring with us organisms that have been engineered to adapt to new and harsh environments. In essence, using engineered organisms to help us terraform a planet both in the short and long term. These organisms can then also be engineered to make medicine or fuel.
So we can use synthetic biology to bring highly engineered plants with us, but what else can we do? Well, I mentioned earlier that we, as a species, were evolved uniquely for planet Earth. That fact has not changed much in the last five minutes that you were sitting here and I was standing there. And so, if we were to dump any of us on Mars right this minute, even given ample food, water, air and a suit, we are likely to experience very unpleasant health problems from the amount of ionizing radiation that bombards the surface of planets like Mars that have little or nonexistent atmosphere. Unless we plan to stay holed up underground for the duration of our stay on every new planet, we must find better ways of protecting ourselves without needing to resort to wearing a suit of armor that weighs something equal to your own body weight, or needing to hide behind a wall of lead.
So let us appeal to nature for inspiration. Among the plethora of life here on Earth, there's a subset of organisms known as extremophiles, or lovers of extreme living conditions, if you'll remember from high school biology. And among these organisms is a bacterium by the name of Deinococcus radiodurans. It is known to be able to withstand cold, dehydration, vacuum, acid, and, most notably, radiation. While its radiation tolerance mechanisms are known, we have yet to adapt the relevant genes to mammals. To do so is not particularly easy. There are many facets that go into its radiation tolerance, and it's not as simple as transferring one gene. But given a little bit of human ingenuity and a little bit of time, I think to do so is not very hard either. Even if we borrow just a fraction of its ability to tolerate radiation, it would be infinitely better than what we already have, which is just the melanin in our skin. Using the tools of synthetic biology, we can harness Deinococcus radiodurans' ability to thrive under otherwise very lethal doses of radiation. As difficult as it is to see, homo sapiens, that is humans, evolves every day, and still continues to evolve. Thousands of years of human evolution has not only given us humans like Tibetans, who can thrive in low-oxygen conditions, but also Argentinians, who can ingest and metabolize arsenic, the chemical element that can kill the average human being. Every day, the human body evolves by accidental mutations that equally accidentally allow certain humans to persevere in dismal situations.
But, and this is a big but, such evolution requires two things that we may not always have, or be able to afford, and they are death and time. In our species' struggle to find our place in the universe, we may not always have the time necessary for the natural evolution of extra functions for survival on non-Earth planets. We're living in what E.O. Wilson has termed the age of gene circumvention, during which we remedy our genetic defects like cystic fibrosis or muscular dystrophy with temporary external supplements. But with every passing day, we approach the age of volitional evolution, a time during which we as a species will have the capacity to decide for ourselves our own genetic destiny. Augmenting the human body with new abilities is no longer a question of how, but of when.
Using synthetic biology to change the genetic makeup of any living organisms, especially our own, is not without its moral and ethical quandaries. Will engineering ourselves make us less human? But then again, what is humanity but star stuff that happens to be conscious? Where should human genius direct itself? Surely it is a bit of a waste to sit back and marvel at it. How do we use our knowledge to protect ourselves from the external dangers and then protect ourselves from ourselves?
I pose these questions not to engender the fear of science but to bring to light the many possibilities that science has afforded and continues to afford us. We must coalesce as humans to discuss and embrace the solutions not only with caution but also with courage.
Mars is a destination, but it will not be our last. Our true final frontier is the line we must cross in deciding what we can and should make of our species' improbable intelligence.
Space is cold, brutal and unforgiving. Our path to the stars will be rife with trials that will bring us to question not only who we are but where we will be going. The answers will lie in our choice to use or abandon the technology that we have gleaned from life itself, and it will define us for the remainder of our term in this universe.
Thank you.
(Applause)</content>
</file>
<file id="3">
  <head>
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/dan_gross_why_gun_violence_can_t_be_our_new_normal</url>
    <pagesize>75482</pagesize>
    <dtime>Fri Apr 01 00:57:21 CEST 2016</dtime>
    <encoding>UTF-8</encoding>
    <content-type>text/html; charset=utf-8</content-type>
    <keywords>talks, Debate, Guns, activism, big problems, children, choice, community, future, goal-setting, government, law, leadership, marketing, parenting, policy, social change, violence</keywords>
    <speaker>Dan Gross</speaker>
    <talkid>2472</talkid>
    <videourl>http://download.ted.com/talks/DanGross_2016.mp4</videourl>
    <videopath>talks/DanGross_2016.mp4</videopath>
    <date>2016/02/17</date>
    <title>Dan Gross: Why gun violence can't be our new normal</title>
    <description>TED Talk Subtitles and Transcript: It doesn't matter whether you love or hate guns; it's obvious that the US would be a safer place if there weren't thousands of them sold every day without background checks. Dan Gross, president of the Brady Campaign to Prevent Gun Violence, makes a passionate, personal appeal for something that more than 90 percent of Americans want: background checks for all gun sales. "For every great movement around the world, there's a moment where you can look back and say, 'That's when things really started to change,'" Gross says. "For the movement to end gun violence in America, that moment is here."</description>
    <transcription>
      <seekvideo id="644">OK, so, confession:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="2502">I've always been weirdly obsessed with advertising.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="8238">I remember watching Saturday morning cartoons,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="11330">paying more attention to the commercials</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="13487">than to the shows,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="14818">trying to figure out how they were trying to get inside my head.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="17932">Ultimately, that led me to my dream job.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="20035">I became a partner at a big New York ad agency.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="23337">But then, all of that suddenly changed on February 23, 1997,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="29550">when my little brother Matt was shot in the head</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="32922">in a shooting that happened on the observation deck</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="35771">of the Empire State Building.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="37911">Suddenly, my family was thrown into the middle of a nightmare,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="43097">being told that my brother was going to die,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="47251">actually being given the opportunity to say goodbye to him,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="50951">then several emergency brain surgeries</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="53325">and now what's amounted, for Matt,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="56000">to a lifetime spent courageously recovering from a traumatic brain injury.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="62270">He is definitely my hero.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="65101">But as much as (Applause) -- yeah, deserves it --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="67467">(Applause)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="72597">But as much as this tragedy was a nightmare for my family,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="78224">I often think about how much worse it could have been;</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="80799">in fact, how much worse it is for the 90 families every day</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="85882">who aren't as fortunate,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="87786">who lose loved ones -- brothers, sisters, sons, daughters, parents.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="94018">They don't all make national headlines.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="96543">In fact, most of them don't.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="98209">They go largely unnoticed,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="100305">in a nation that's kind of come to accept a disgraceful national epidemic</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="106928">as some kind of new normal.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="110800">So I quit my job in advertising</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="113170">to try and do something about this disgraceful national epidemic,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="118296">because I came to realize</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="119517">that the challenges to preventing gun violence</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="122654">are actually the same ones that made me love advertising,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="126343">which is to try to figure out how to engage people.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="128850">Only instead of doing it to sell products,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="131477">doing it to save lives.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="133726">And that comes down to finding common ground,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="138673">where what I want overlaps with what you want.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="142706">And you might be surprised to learn, when it comes to gun violence,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="145936">just how much common ground there is.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="148007">Let's look, for example, at people who love to hunt,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="151016">a sport enjoyed by millions across the US.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="154222">It's a proud tradition. Families.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="156886">In some places,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="158064">the first day of hunting season is actually a school holiday.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="161821">What do hunters want?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="163285">Well, they want to hunt. They love their guns.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="165657">They believe deeply</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="166881">in the Second Amendment right to own those guns.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="169397">But that doesn't mean there isn't common ground.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="171700">In fact, there's a lot of it,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="173152">starting with the basic idea of keeping guns out of dangerous hands.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="178580">This isn't about taking certain guns away from all people.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="183418">It's about keeping all guns away from certain people,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="186318">and it's the people that, it turns out, we all agree shouldn't have guns:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="189807">convicted violent criminals, domestic abusers,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="192311">the dangerously mentally ill.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="195205">We can all appreciate</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="196380">how Brady background checks have been incredibly effective</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="199311">in keeping guns out of those dangerous hands.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="201603">In 20 years, Brady background checks at federally licensed firearm dealers</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="206034">have blocked 2.4 million gun sales</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="209823">to those people that we all agree shouldn't have guns.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="213463">(Applause)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="217410">And whether you love guns or hate guns, you probably also appreciate</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="221631">that there shouldn't be thousands of gun sales every day</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="224831">at guns shows or online</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="226701">without those Brady background checks,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="228584">just like there shouldn't be two lines to get on an airplane --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="231608">one with security and one with no security.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="234256">And --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="235431">(Applause)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="238957">And the numbers show the overwhelming agreement among the American public:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="242744">90 percent of Americans support expanding Brady background checks</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="247051">to all gun sales -- including 90 percent of Republicans,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="249709">more than 80 percent of gun owners,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="251653">more than 70 percent of NRA members.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="253929">This is not a controversial idea.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="255867">In fact, only six percent of the American public disagrees.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="259467">That's about the percentage of the American public</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="261856">that believes the moon landing was a fake.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="264069">(Laughter)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="265458">And it's also about the percentage that believes the government</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="268454">is putting mind-controlling technology in our TV broadcast signals.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="272437">That's the extent to which we agree about background checks.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="275288">But what about the 300 million guns</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="278860">already out there in homes across America?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="281280">Well first, it's important to realize</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="283074">that those guns are mostly in the hands and homes</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="287436">of decent, law-abiding people like you and me,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="290400">who want what we all want -- including keeping our families safe.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="294695">In fact, that's why more and more people are choosing to own guns.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="298704">Ten years ago, 42 percent of the American public</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="303063">believed -- incorrectly -- that a gun makes your home safer.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="307364">Today, that number is 63 percent.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="311784">Why?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="312960">I kind of hate to say it,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="314182">because it gets to the dark underbelly of advertising,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="316796">which is if you tell a big enough lie enough times,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="319248">eventually that lie becomes the truth.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="321113">And that's exactly what's happened here.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="323084">The corporate gun lobby has spent billions of dollars</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="325650">blocking the CDC from doing research into the public health epidemic</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="328999">of gun violence;</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="330684">blocking pediatricians from talking to parents</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="332868">about the dangers of guns in the home;</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="334703">blocking smart-gun technology and other technology</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="337096">that would prevent kids from firing parents' guns</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="339791">and would save lives.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="341812">They're desperate to hide the truth,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="344105">because they view the truth as a threat to their bottom line.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="348407">And every day,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="349592">people are dying as a result.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="351211">And a lot of those people are children.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="354108">Every day in the US,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="356469">nine kids are just shot unintentionally.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="360309">900 children and teens take their own lives every year.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="365476">And here's the thing: they're almost all with a parent's gun.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="369874">Even two-thirds of school shootings happen with a gun taken from the home,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="376259">including the terrible tragedy</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="377968">at Sandy Hook.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="379562">I meet so many of these parents;</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="381549">it's the most heartbreaking part of my job.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="384379">These are not bad people.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="387476">They're just living with the unimaginable consequences of a very bad decision,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="392715">made based on very bad information</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="395610">that was put into their minds by very bad people,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="398522">who know good and well the misery that they're causing,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="401751">but just don't care.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="404577">And the result is a nightmare --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="407063">not only for families like mine,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="409657">but for, really, at the end of the day, all of us.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="413472">But I'm not here to talk about the nightmare of gun violence.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="416410">I'm here to talk about our dream, and it's a dream we all share,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="419470">which is the dream of a better, safer, future.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="421970">For my organization, for the Brady Campaign,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="424696">that dream is reflected in the bold goal</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="427308">to cut the number of gun deaths in the US in half by 2025.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="432102">And I hope to leave all of you here tonight</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="434628">with a strong sense of exactly why that dream is so absolutely within reach.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="440525">Because folks,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="441915">for every great movement around the world,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="444751">there's a moment where you can look back and say,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="447562">"That's when things really started to change."</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="451065">And I'm here to say</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="452313">that for the movement to end gun violence in America,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="455258">that moment is here.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="458308">(Applause)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="463993">We are so clearly at a tipping point,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="466898">because the American public has come together by the millions</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="470033">like never before, based on that common ground,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="472271">to say, "Enough."</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="473690">Enough of the mass shootings in malls and movie theaters</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="476921">and churches and schools.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="478851">Enough of the daily terror of gun violence in homes and streets</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="483768">that's claimed the lives of women and young black men</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="486999">in staggering proportions.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="488445">Enough of easy access to guns</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="490252">by the people that we all agree shouldn't have them.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="492752">And enough of a small group of craven politicians</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="495811">putting the interests of the corporate gun lobby</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="498124">ahead of the people they have been elected to represent.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="501147">Enough.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="502322">(Applause)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="508500">And the really exciting thing is, it's not just the usual suspects like me</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="512428">that are saying it anymore.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="513984">It's so much bigger than that.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="515912">And if you want proof,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="517087">let's start where most conversations in the US seem to start --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="520663">with Kim Kardashian.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="522091">(Laughter)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="523305">And here's the thing: it's not really a joke.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="525448">I mean, think about when issues change.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="527345">It's when they go from being political and advocacy issues</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="530138">to being part of pop culture,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="531568">voices coming from everywhere, celebrities using their platforms,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="535161">musicians, athletes.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="536786">The NBA has come forward.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="538066">Conservative pundits that you never would have imagined</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="540744">have come forward.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="541919">There's real cultural change --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="543485">I even hear there's a TED Talk about it this year.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="545875">That's the extent to which this cultural change is happening.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="550444">And yes, Kim Kardashian has made an unsolicited passionate appeal</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="554396">to her 35 million Twitter followers</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="557534">for expanded background checks.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="559906">Let's look at the political elections that are heating up.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="562845">This used to be the classic third-rail issue for Democrats.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="565726">Couldn't run from it fast enough.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="567464">Now candidates are running on it.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="569171">Some are being forced to reverse very bad positions</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="572162">they defended very comfortably, until very recently.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="576408">For somebody like me,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="578062">watching people wave around their negative NRA ratings --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="583148">it's almost surreal to watch.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="586391">We're still outfunded, yes, by the corporate gun lobby,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="590138">and ultimately that needs to change.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="592531">But you know what?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="593716">We're smarter and we're scrappier, and we have the truth on our side.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="598099">And we're on offense.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="599843">You know, they say that the Internet democratizes information.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="603277">Social media and some of the organizing tools that plug into it</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="607039">have democratized activism.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="608936">It's allowed us to show what 90 percent support really looks like.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="612327">Sometimes I think of it --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="613598">you know, we're converging and attacking instantly by the millions,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="616859">kind of like white blood cells.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="618486">It's enabled us to start to really close -- and this is the bottom line --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="623069">close that disgraceful disconnect</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="625299">between what the American public wants</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="627735">and what our elected leaders are doing about it.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="630006">Until recently,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="631554">the narrative in Congress was that calls from the other side,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="634830">from that six percent,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="636014">outnumbered calls from our side 10 to one.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="639218">We're flipping that narrative on its head.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="641281">After that recent terrible tragedy in San Bernardino,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="643915">we jammed Congressional switchboards.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="645744">We put 15,000 calls into Congress in 24 hours.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="651141">And you know what?</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="652316">We got a vote on a bill</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="653491">that nobody thought was going to see the light of day anytime soon.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="656729">We're seeing real movement to repeal some of the most evil,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="659594">ugly gun lobby legislation passed over the last dark decade.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="664257">The stranglehold of the gun lobby is clearly being broken.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="667188">We've seen President Obama's historic executive actions.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="670514">They don't go all the way,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="671928">but they are going to save lives,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="673539">because they expand Brady background checks</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="675610">to thousands of gun sales that didn't have them previously.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="679206">And we're marching across the country -- we're not just waiting</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="682238">for Congress to act; that would almost be the definition of insanity.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="685647">We're marching across the country,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="687316">state by state, marriage-equality style.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="689939">And you know what? We're winning.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="691537">Congress is almost always the last to wake up and realize</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="695228">that it's on the wrong side of history.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="697441">And when they do, it's always because the American public shakes them.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="701086">And that's exactly what we're doing right now,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="703292">as we're in this tipping point.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="704854">You know, recently I was flying cross-country to give a speech</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="708827">to a large group like this, although far less intimidating,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="712283">and the woman sitting next to me happened to be binge-watching</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="716048">one of my all-time favorite TV shows, "Mad Men,"</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="721000">a period TV show about advertising</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="723238">in the 1960s.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="725080">And as I was trying to think about how to end my remarks,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="728701">I'd glance up at her screen every now and then,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="731000">and it seemed that every time I did,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="733317">I'd see somebody smoking in an office or around children</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="737666">or while pregnant or drinking and driving</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="740103">or driving without seat belts or sexually harassing a coworker.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="744098">And ultimately it dawned on me:</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="746496">what tremendous inspiration</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="747882">to those of us who have this dream to end gun violence.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="751865">I mean, think about how much the world has changed</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="754460">in a relatively short period of time,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="757263">how all those behaviors that were once considered commonplace or normal --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="760920">some even glamorous or sexy --</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="763161">have become stigmatized in just a generation or two,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="767292">once they became conversations about our common ground.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="771799">That is the magnitude of the change we have the potential to create</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="776637">around gun violence.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="778296">And that's my dream,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="779884">that maybe someday,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="781376">some period TV show will depict the terrible nightmare of gun violence,</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="786895">and a future generation of children might only be able to imagine</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="790293">how terrible it must have been.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="792166">Thank you.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="793341">(Applause)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="799079">Thank you.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="800254">(Applause)</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="801771">Thank you.</seekvideo>
      <seekvideo id="802946">(Applause)</seekvideo>
    </transcription>
    <wordnum>2108</wordnum>
    <charnum>12090</charnum>
  </head>
  <content>OK, so, confession: I've always been weirdly obsessed with advertising. I remember watching Saturday morning cartoons, paying more attention to the commercials than to the shows, trying to figure out how they were trying to get inside my head. Ultimately, that led me to my dream job. I became a partner at a big New York ad agency.
But then, all of that suddenly changed on February 23, 1997, when my little brother Matt was shot in the head in a shooting that happened on the observation deck of the Empire State Building. Suddenly, my family was thrown into the middle of a nightmare, being told that my brother was going to die, actually being given the opportunity to say goodbye to him, then several emergency brain surgeries and now what's amounted, for Matt, to a lifetime spent courageously recovering from a traumatic brain injury. He is definitely my hero.
But as much as (Applause) -- yeah, deserves it --
(Applause)
But as much as this tragedy was a nightmare for my family, I often think about how much worse it could have been; in fact, how much worse it is for the 90 families every day who aren't as fortunate, who lose loved ones -- brothers, sisters, sons, daughters, parents. They don't all make national headlines. In fact, most of them don't. They go largely unnoticed, in a nation that's kind of come to accept a disgraceful national epidemic as some kind of new normal.
So I quit my job in advertising to try and do something about this disgraceful national epidemic, because I came to realize that the challenges to preventing gun violence are actually the same ones that made me love advertising, which is to try to figure out how to engage people. Only instead of doing it to sell products, doing it to save lives. And that comes down to finding common ground, where what I want overlaps with what you want. And you might be surprised to learn, when it comes to gun violence, just how much common ground there is.
Let's look, for example, at people who love to hunt, a sport enjoyed by millions across the US. It's a proud tradition. Families. In some places, the first day of hunting season is actually a school holiday. What do hunters want? Well, they want to hunt. They love their guns. They believe deeply in the Second Amendment right to own those guns. But that doesn't mean there isn't common ground.
In fact, there's a lot of it, starting with the basic idea of keeping guns out of dangerous hands. This isn't about taking certain guns away from all people. It's about keeping all guns away from certain people, and it's the people that, it turns out, we all agree shouldn't have guns: convicted violent criminals, domestic abusers, the dangerously mentally ill. We can all appreciate how Brady background checks have been incredibly effective in keeping guns out of those dangerous hands. In 20 years, Brady background checks at federally licensed firearm dealers have blocked 2.4 million gun sales to those people that we all agree shouldn't have guns.
(Applause)
And whether you love guns or hate guns, you probably also appreciate that there shouldn't be thousands of gun sales every day at guns shows or online without those Brady background checks, just like there shouldn't be two lines to get on an airplane -- one with security and one with no security. And --
(Applause)
And the numbers show the overwhelming agreement among the American public: 90 percent of Americans support expanding Brady background checks to all gun sales -- including 90 percent of Republicans, more than 80 percent of gun owners, more than 70 percent of NRA members. This is not a controversial idea. In fact, only six percent of the American public disagrees. That's about the percentage of the American public that believes the moon landing was a fake.
(Laughter)
And it's also about the percentage that believes the government is putting mind-controlling technology in our TV broadcast signals. That's the extent to which we agree about background checks.
But what about the 300 million guns already out there in homes across America? Well first, it's important to realize that those guns are mostly in the hands and homes of decent, law-abiding people like you and me, who want what we all want -- including keeping our families safe. In fact, that's why more and more people are choosing to own guns. Ten years ago, 42 percent of the American public believed -- incorrectly -- that a gun makes your home safer. Today, that number is 63 percent.
Why? I kind of hate to say it, because it gets to the dark underbelly of advertising, which is if you tell a big enough lie enough times, eventually that lie becomes the truth. And that's exactly what's happened here. The corporate gun lobby has spent billions of dollars blocking the CDC from doing research into the public health epidemic of gun violence; blocking pediatricians from talking to parents about the dangers of guns in the home; blocking smart-gun technology and other technology that would prevent kids from firing parents' guns and would save lives. They're desperate to hide the truth, because they view the truth as a threat to their bottom line.
And every day, people are dying as a result. And a lot of those people are children. Every day in the US, nine kids are just shot unintentionally. 900 children and teens take their own lives every year. And here's the thing: they're almost all with a parent's gun. Even two-thirds of school shootings happen with a gun taken from the home, including the terrible tragedy at Sandy Hook. I meet so many of these parents; it's the most heartbreaking part of my job. These are not bad people. They're just living with the unimaginable consequences of a very bad decision, made based on very bad information that was put into their minds by very bad people, who know good and well the misery that they're causing, but just don't care. And the result is a nightmare -- not only for families like mine, but for, really, at the end of the day, all of us.
But I'm not here to talk about the nightmare of gun violence. I'm here to talk about our dream, and it's a dream we all share, which is the dream of a better, safer, future. For my organization, for the Brady Campaign, that dream is reflected in the bold goal to cut the number of gun deaths in the US in half by 2025. And I hope to leave all of you here tonight with a strong sense of exactly why that dream is so absolutely within reach. Because folks, for every great movement around the world, there's a moment where you can look back and say, "That's when things really started to change." And I'm here to say that for the movement to end gun violence in America, that moment is here.
(Applause)
We are so clearly at a tipping point, because the American public has come together by the millions like never before, based on that common ground, to say, "Enough." Enough of the mass shootings in malls and movie theaters and churches and schools. Enough of the daily terror of gun violence in homes and streets that's claimed the lives of women and young black men in staggering proportions. Enough of easy access to guns by the people that we all agree shouldn't have them. And enough of a small group of craven politicians putting the interests of the corporate gun lobby ahead of the people they have been elected to represent. Enough.
(Applause)
And the really exciting thing is, it's not just the usual suspects like me that are saying it anymore. It's so much bigger than that. And if you want proof, let's start where most conversations in the US seem to start -- with Kim Kardashian.
(Laughter)
And here's the thing: it's not really a joke. I mean, think about when issues change. It's when they go from being political and advocacy issues to being part of pop culture, voices coming from everywhere, celebrities using their platforms, musicians, athletes. The NBA has come forward. Conservative pundits that you never would have imagined have come forward. There's real cultural change -- I even hear there's a TED Talk about it this year. That's the extent to which this cultural change is happening. And yes, Kim Kardashian has made an unsolicited passionate appeal to her 35 million Twitter followers for expanded background checks.
Let's look at the political elections that are heating up. This used to be the classic third-rail issue for Democrats. Couldn't run from it fast enough. Now candidates are running on it. Some are being forced to reverse very bad positions they defended very comfortably, until very recently. For somebody like me, watching people wave around their negative NRA ratings -- it's almost surreal to watch. We're still outfunded, yes, by the corporate gun lobby, and ultimately that needs to change. But you know what? We're smarter and we're scrappier, and we have the truth on our side. And we're on offense.
You know, they say that the Internet democratizes information. Social media and some of the organizing tools that plug into it have democratized activism. It's allowed us to show what 90 percent support really looks like. Sometimes I think of it -- you know, we're converging and attacking instantly by the millions, kind of like white blood cells. It's enabled us to start to really close -- and this is the bottom line -- close that disgraceful disconnect between what the American public wants and what our elected leaders are doing about it.
Until recently, the narrative in Congress was that calls from the other side, from that six percent, outnumbered calls from our side 10 to one. We're flipping that narrative on its head. After that recent terrible tragedy in San Bernardino, we jammed Congressional switchboards. We put 15,000 calls into Congress in 24 hours. And you know what? We got a vote on a bill that nobody thought was going to see the light of day anytime soon. We're seeing real movement to repeal some of the most evil, ugly gun lobby legislation passed over the last dark decade. The stranglehold of the gun lobby is clearly being broken. We've seen President Obama's historic executive actions. They don't go all the way, but they are going to save lives, because they expand Brady background checks to thousands of gun sales that didn't have them previously. And we're marching across the country -- we're not just waiting for Congress to act; that would almost be the definition of insanity. We're marching across the country, state by state, marriage-equality style.
And you know what? We're winning. Congress is almost always the last to wake up and realize that it's on the wrong side of history. And when they do, it's always because the American public shakes them. And that's exactly what we're doing right now, as we're in this tipping point.
You know, recently I was flying cross-country to give a speech to a large group like this, although far less intimidating, and the woman sitting next to me happened to be binge-watching one of my all-time favorite TV shows, "Mad Men," a period TV show about advertising in the 1960s. And as I was trying to think about how to end my remarks, I'd glance up at her screen every now and then, and it seemed that every time I did, I'd see somebody smoking in an office or around children or while pregnant or drinking and driving or driving without seat belts or sexually harassing a coworker.
And ultimately it dawned on me: what tremendous inspiration to those of us who have this dream to end gun violence. I mean, think about how much the world has changed in a relatively short period of time, how all those behaviors that were once considered commonplace or normal -- some even glamorous or sexy -- have become stigmatized in just a generation or two, once they became conversations about our common ground. That is the magnitude of the change we have the potential to create around gun violence.
And that's my dream, that maybe someday, some period TV show will depict the terrible nightmare of gun violence, and a future generation of children might only be able to imagine how terrible it must have been.
Thank you.
(Applause)
Thank you.
(Applause)
Thank you.
(Applause)</content>
</file>
</xml>
